I'm here to show you
أنا هنا لأعرض عليكم
how something you can't see can be so much fun to look at.
كيف لشيء لا تستطيع رؤيته يمكن أن يكون من الممتع جداً النظر إليه.
You're about to experience a new, available
أنت ألان على وشك تجربة تكنولوجيا جديدة، متوفرة
and exciting technology that's going to make us rethink
ومثيرة والتي سوف تجعلنا نعيد التفكير
how we waterproof our lives.
في كيف يمكن وقاية حياتنا من الماء.
What I have here is a cinder block
ما لدي هنا هو طابوق
that we've coated half with a nanotechnology spray
و قد قمنا غطينا نصفه برذاذ تقنية النانو
that can be applied to almost any material.
و الذي يمكن تطبيقه تقريباً على أي مادة.
It's called Ultra-Ever Dry,
تدعى هذه Ultra-Ever Dry
and when you apply it to any material,
وعند وضعها على أي مادة،
it turns into a superhydrophobic shield.
فإنه يتحول إلى درع سوبيرهيدروفوبيك.
So this is a cinder block, uncoated,
لذلك هذا الطابوق، غير مصقول،
and you can see that it's porous, it absorbs water.
ويمكنك أن ترى أنه من المسامية، إنه يمتص الماء.
Not anymore.
لكن ليس بعد الآن.
Porous, nonporous.
به مسامات، لا يوجد به مسامات.
So what's superhydrophobic?
فما هو سوبيرهيدروفوبيك؟
Superhydrophobic is how we measure
سوبيرهيدروفوبيك هو كيف نقيس
a drop of water on a surface.
قطره ماء على سطح.
The rounder it is, the more hydrophobic it is,
كل ما ستدارت، كل ما كثر أصبحت hydrophobic،
and if it's really round, it's superhydrophobic.
وإذا كانت حقاً مستديرة، فإنها superhydrophobic .
A freshly waxed car, the water molecules slump
سيارة مشمعة، تنخفض جزيئات الماء
to about 90 degrees.
إلى حوالي 90 درجة.
A windshield coating is going to give you about 110 degrees.
طلاء الزجاج الأمامي سوف تعطيك حوالي 110 درجات.
But what you're seeing here is 160 to 175 degrees,
ولكن ما ترونه هنا 160 إلى 175 درجة،
and anything over 150 is superhydrophobic.
وأي شيء أكثر من 150 يعتبر superhydrophobic.
So as part of the demonstration,
كجزء من هذا العرض،
what I have is a pair of gloves,
ما لدي هنا هو زوج من القفازات،
and we've coated one of the gloves
و قد قمنا بتغطية واحدة من القفازات
with the nanotechnology coating,
بطلاء تكنولوجيا النانو،
and let's see if you can tell which one,
دعونا نرى إذا كان يمكنكم معرفة أي واحد،
and I'll give you a hint.
وسوف أعطيك تلميحاً.
Did you guess the one that was dry?
هل يمكنك تخمين أي واحد كان جافاً؟
When you have nanotechnology and nanoscience,
عندما يكون لديك تكنولوجيا النانو وعلم النانو،
what's occurred is that we're able to now
ما يحدث هو أنه يمكننا من الآن
look at atoms and molecules and actually control them
إلقاء نظرة على الذرات والجزيئات والسيطرة عليها فعلا
for great benefits.
للحصول على فوائد كبيرة.
And we're talking really small here.
ونحن نتحدث هنا حقاً عن مواد صغيرة.
The way you measure nanotechnology is in nanometers,
الطريقة التي يمكنك قياس تكنولوجيا النانو هي عن طريق النانومتر،
and one nanometer is a billionth of a meter,
واحد نانومتر هوعبارة عن واحد من مليار متري،
and to put some scale to that,
لوضع ذلك لقياس،
if you had a nanoparticle that was one nanometer thick,
إذا كان لديك مادة نانو والتي سمكها واحد نانومتر،
and you put it side by side, and you had 50,000 of them,
وضعتها جنبا إلى جنب، وكان لديك 50,000 منهم،
you'd be the width of a human hair.
سيكون عرضها كعُرض شعره الإنسان.
So very small, but very useful.
هي صغيرة جداً، لكنها مفيدة جداً.
And it's not just water that this works with.
وليست فقط المياه التي تعمل معها.
It's a lot of water-based materials like concrete,
يوجد الكثير من المواد القائمة على الماء مثل الخرسانة،
water-based paint,
الطلاء المائي،
mud,
الطين،
and also some refined oils as well.
وأيضا بعض الزيوت المكررة كذلك.
You can see the difference.
يمكنك أن ترى الفرق.
Moving onto the next demonstration,
بإنتقالنا الى العرض القادم،
we've taken a pane of glass and we've coated the outside of it,
لقد أخذنا جزء من زجاج وقمنا بتغطيتة من الخارج،
we've framed it with the nanotechnology coating,
وشكلناه بغطاء تكنلوجيا النانو
and we're going to pour this green-tinted water inside the middle,
سوف نقوم بصب هذا الماء الملون بالأخضر بالداخل
and you're going to see, it's going to spread out on glass
وسوف تشاهدون، هذا الماء ينتشر داخل الزجاج
like you'd normally think it would,
مثل ما تتوقعون عادة ،
except when it hits the coating, it stops,
غير أنه عندما يلامس الطلاء، فإنه يتوقف،
and I can't even coax it to leave.
ولا يمكنني حتى أجعله يخرج.
It's that afraid of the water.
أنه يخاف من الماء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So what's going on here? What's happening?
ما يحدث هنا أذاً ؟ ماذا يحدث؟
Well, the surface of the spray coating
حسنا، سطح رذاذ الطلاء
is actually filled with nanoparticles
في الواقع مليء بجسيمات نانوية
that form a very rough and craggly surface.
من سطح خشن و صخري جداً.
You'd think it'd be smooth, but it's actually not.
مما يجعلكم تعتقدون أنه سوف سيكون سلساً، ولكن هو في الواقع غير ذلك.
And it has billions of interstitial spaces,
ولديه مليارات من المساحات المتداخلة،
and those spaces, along with the nanoparticles,
وتلك المساحات، جنبا إلى جنب مع جسيمات نانوية،
reach up and grab the air molecules,
تصل ونتزع جزيئات الهواء،
and cover the surface with air.
وتغطي السطح بالهواء.
It's an umbrella of air all across it,
أنها مظلة للهواء وكل شيء عبره،
and that layer of air is what the water hits,
وهذه الطبقة من الهواء هي ما يصطدم بها الماء،
the mud hits, the concrete hits, and it glides right off.
ويصطدم بها الطين، ويصطدم بها الأسمنت، وتنسل منه.
So if I put this inside this water here,
لذلك إذا وضعت هذا إلى داخل الماء هنا،
you can see a silver reflective coating around it,
يمكنكم أن ترؤن طلاء فضي عاكس حوله،
and that silver reflective coating
وهذا طلاء الفضي العاكس
is the layer of air that's protecting the water
هو طبقة من الهواء التي تقوم بحماية الماء
from touching the paddle, and it's dry.
من ملامسة للمجداف، و تبقى جافة.
So what are the applications?
فما هي التطبيقات؟
I mean, many of you right now are probably going through your head.
أعني الكثير منكم الآن على الأرجح تفكرون.
Everyone that sees this gets excited, and says,
جميع من يرى هذا يصبح متحمس، ويقول:
"Oh, I could use it for this and this and this."
"أوه، يمكنني إستخدامها لهذا وهذا وهذا."
The applications in a general sense
بشكل عام الأستخدامات
could be anything that's anti-wetting.
قد تكون لأي شيء ضد التبلل
We've certainly seen that today.
رأينا ذلك بكل التأكيد اليوم.
It could be anything that's anti-icing,
قد تكون لأي شيء ضد التجمد،
because if you don't have water, you don't have ice.
لأنه إذا لم يكن لديك الماء، لم يكن لديك الجليد.
It could be anti-corrosion.
قد تكون لأي شيء ضد التآكل.
No water, no corrosion.
لا ماء، لا تآكل.
It could be anti-bacterial.
يمكن أن يكون مضاد للبكتيريا.
Without water, the bacteria won't survive.
بدون الماء، لن تعيش البكتيريا.
And it could be things that need to be self-cleaning as well.
ويمكن أن يكون للأشياء التي تحتاج التنظيف الذاتي أيضاً.
So imagine how something like this
لذا تخيل كيف لشيئاً من هذا القبيل
could help revolutionize your field of work.
أن يساعد على أحداث ثورة في مجال العمل الخاص بك.
And I'm going to leave you with one last demonstration,
سوف أترككم مع مشهد أخير،
but before I do that, I would like to say thank you,
ولكن قبل أن أفعل ذلك، أود أن أقول لكم شكرا،
and think small.
وفكروا بشكل مصغر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's going to happen. Wait for it. Wait for it.
سوف تحدث.أنتظروها. أنتظروها
Chris Anderson: You guys didn't hear about us cutting out the Design from TED? (Laughter)
كريس أندرسون: يا رفاق لم تسمعوا عن قصصنا نموذج TED ؟ (ضحك)
[Two minutes later...]
[بعد دقيقتين...]
He ran into all sorts of problems in terms of managing the medical research part.
هو يواجه كل أنواع المشاكل من حيث إدارة البحوث الطبية.
It's happening!
ذلك يحدث!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)